A Guide to the Wampler Business Records, 1916-1972: SC 0202
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Wampler Business Records,
1916-1972
Special Collections, James Madison University
Wampler, Charles Weldon, Sr., 1885-1976
SC 0202
11 cubic feet; 31 boxes
This collection contains correspondence, reports, photographs, business documents, financial statements, publications, and other documents that relate to the businesses of Charles Wampler Sr. (Wampler Feed and Seed Company) primarily and to a lesser degree his son, Charles Wampler Jr. (Wampler Food Incorporated). Correspondence comprises the bulk of the collection.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Barbara W. Melby, daughter of Charles W. Wampler Jr., and Lawrence D. Bowers in May 2009.
Provenance
The bulk of this collection came from the Wampler family's Sunny Slope Farm Property near Dayton, Virginia. In 2009, James Madison University history professor Daniel Kerr was in communication with Barbara Melby, daughter of Charles W. Wampler Jr., who occupied the Sunny Slope property at that time. Mrs. Melby identified the storage of documents within the barn. After an initial inspection of the material, arrangements to transfer the material to Special Collections for cleaning, rehousing, and processing were made.
Bio/Historical Note
The Wampler family emerged upon the American poultry industry in the early twentieth century changing the industry practices and beliefs. As a result of their success, the Wamplers became one of the most influential families in Rockingham County, Virginia and helped the Shenandoah Valley garner the moniker "Turkey Capital of the Nation."
In 1811, John Wampler and family, members of the Brethren Church, moved from Pennsylvania to the Timberville area of the county during a period when large groups of Brethren were migrating south. During the Civil War, John Wampler III gained notoriety for supposedly thwarting Union General Philip Sheridan's attempt to burn his family's barn. After the war, in 1871, John Wampler III purchased a farm in Dayton that he named Sunny Slope and built a house there. Under the setting of Sunny Slope, John Wampler III's children and grandchildren made their many significant contributions to agriculture.
Charles W. Wampler Sr., third son of John Wampler III, was born in 1886 and took quickly to the agricultural development of the county. He became a county agricultural agent and was an accomplished livestock farmer raising chickens and cattle. Eventually, he settled into turkey farming and started Rockingham County's first turkey hatchery. It was during this time that he became known as the "Father of the Modern Turkey Industry" because of his success in various agricultural experiments that changed the face of modern turkey farming. One of his earliest experiments was using chicken incubators to hatch turkey eggs. Starting with only ninety eggs, Wampler Sr. was able to hatch fifty-two poults. Another Charles Wampler Sr. innovation all but ended the wide spread practice of free-range turkey farming in commercial operations. Wampler Sr. believed, and was able to show, that free-range turkeys were less cost effective to raise as they expended more energy and required more feed at the expense of the farmer. Wampler practiced "incubation and confinement" which soon became the standard among successful poultry growers.
Charles Wampler Sr. also served as the first Rockingham County Extension Agent and founded the Wampler Feed and Seed Company in 1927 with two of his brothers. The company mixed feed for distribution to livestock and turkeys. Wampler Feed and Seed was the first in the nation to contract with farms to grow poultry. Wampler also helped found the National Turkey Federation. Among his many philanthropic activities, Charles Wampler Sr. served on the Board of Trustees for Bridgewater College, on the Board of Visitors for Virginia Polytechnic Institute, and on the Board of Directors for the Children's Home Society of Virginia.
Charles Wampler Jr. was born at Sunny Slope on November 25, 1915 as one of nine children (six daughters and three sons.) He attended Bridgewater College for two years and Rutgers University for one year. His early indoctrination in the poultry business began at the age of seven when he and a sister, with the aid of their mother, prepared feed for turkeys in the family business. Crushed eggs and oatmeal were the two main components of the feed. In 1936, his career officially began as a "field man" for Wampler Feed and Seed - traveling to various growers and inspecting livestock. Eventually, Charles Jr. became the company's general manager when Charles Sr. retired. In 1969, Wampler hatcheries, feed mills, and grower operations joined with Virginia Valley Processing to become Wampler Food Incorporated. Poultry processing, hatcheries, and growers were combined as a single corporation with Charles Wampler Jr. as president. In 1984, Charles Jr. oversaw the merger between Wampler Foods and Longacre Farms out of Franconia, Pennsylvania. By 1986, Wampler-Longacre acquired the Rockingham Poultry Cooperative and formed WLR Foods Incorporated with Charles Jr. as chairman of the board.
In addition to his business career, Charles Wampler Jr. had an equally distinguished career in service. Charles Jr. was a district representative for Rockingham County in the Virginia House of Delegates from 1954 until 1965 serving on several committees including Agriculture, Finance, and Labor. In 1957, he co-founded the United Way of Harrisonburg and Rockingham County. From 1971 to 1984, Charles Jr. served as president and chairman of the board for the Rockingham Memorial Hospital. He has also served on James Madison University's Board of Visitors and the Rockingham County School Board. In 1990, he received James Madison University's Common Wealth award in recognition of outstanding contributions to the community. In addition, Charles Wampler Jr. was a member of the Church of the Brethren in Harrisonburg.
Scope and Content
The Wampler Family Business Records, 1916-1972, consists of 11 cubic feet and 31 boxes of material documenting Wampler Foods Incorporated. The collection is primarily comprised of personal and business correspondence of Charles Wampler Sr. The collection includes bound ledgers, financial documents, print material, reports, memoranda, and pictures. The collection is arranged topically into eleven series. Series include Administrative Files, Correspondence, Date Books, Farm Ledgers, Financial Papers, Philanthropy and Professional Organizations, Photographs, Press and Advertising Files, Print and Ephemera, Reports and Studies, and Business and Organization lists.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically by topic in the following ten series:
Series 1: Administrative Files, 1937-1972
Series 2: Correspondence, 1918-1971
Series 3: Date Books, 1939-1965
Series 4: Farm Ledgers, 1932-1951
Series 5: Financial Files, 1941-1971
Series 6: Philanthropic and Professional Organizations, 1939-1971
Series 7: Photographs, 1939-1971
Series 8: Press and Advertising Files, 1920-1963
Series 9: Print and Ephemera, 1916-1971
Series 10: Reports and Studies, 1927-1969
Series 11: Business and Organization lists, 1941-1967
Related Materials
Elizabeth "Libby" Custer Papers, ca.1930s-1997, SC 0077, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, Va.
Wampler Family Papers, 1798-1962, SC 0150, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, VA
Separated Material
Several publications relating to local matters were pulled from the collection, cataloged individuallly, and added to Special Collections' rare book holdings.
Bibliography
Charles W. Wampler Jr., interview by Jessica Silveri, March 15, 2007, transcript, Shenandoah Valley Oral History Project, Harrisonburg, VA. Virginia House of Delegates.
Historical Bio for Charles W. Wampler. Virginia House of Delegates. http://dela.state.va.us/dela/Membios.nsf/94f6e9b9c9b5678f85256b1b00732227/024c8d9337c5d82485256d780068407b?OpenDocument&Highlight=0,charles,Wampler (accessed May 04, 2011).
Wampler, Charles W. My Grandfather, my grandchildren and me; an autobiography. Harrisonburg, VA; Dayton, VA: Shenandoah Press, 1968.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Wampler, Charles W., 1885-1976; Wampler, Charles W., 1915-2017; Wampler family; Wampler family -- Correspondence; Wampler Feed & Seed Co. -- History; Wampler Foods Incorporated -- History; Sunny Slope (Dayton, Va.: Estate); Family-owned business enterprises -- Virginia; Agricultural industries -- Equipment and supplies; Agriculture -- Economic aspects; Agricultural extension workers; Farm management; Farm supplies; Poultry -- Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.); Poultry -- Virginia -- Rockingham County; Poultry -- Breeding; Poultry -- Hatcheries; Poultry industry; Poultry management; Broilers (Chickens) -- Economic aspects -- Virginia; Poultry processing; Seed industry and trade -- History; Seed industry and trade -- Equipment and supplies; Dayton (Va.) -- Industries -- History; Rockingham County (Va.) -- History -- Sources; Virginia -- History, Local -- Sources; Virginia -- Genealogy -- Sources
Genre and Form Terms:
Letters (correspondence); Publications (documents); Administrative records
- Series 1: Administrative Files, 1937-1972
  Scope and Content
  Series 1: Administrative Files, 1937-1972, includes a diverse assortment of administrative documents representing the business' large-scale farming operations. Insurance information and documents represent a large portion of the series regarding farm capital and employees. Another large section of the series is "testing documentation" for the various animals owned and bred by the Wamplers including chickens, turkey, cows, and sheep. Nearly all of these animals required regular government-regulated testing, and the corresponding findings and results are within this series.
  - Insurance Records, 1943-1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Occidental Life Insurance Company of California- Statement of Claim, Nationwide Life Insurance Company- Statement of Claim, Rockingham Home Mutual Fire Insurance Company.
  - Insurance Records, 1960-1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Nationwide Life Insurance Company- Statement of Claim, West Rockingham Mutual Fire Co.
  - Poultry Records, 1956-1962 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Record of Eggs and Poults, Department of Agriculture- Agricultural Marketing Service, Virginia Valley Processors.
  - Sheep Records, 1954-1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Application for Registration of Cheviot Sheep.
  - Soil Records, 1950-1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Soil Record Sheets, Virginia Department of Agriculture- Lime Letter.
  - Farm Records, 1918-1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    United States Department of Agriculture- Bureau of Markets, Agreement between Wampler Feed & Seed Company and Walker May.
  - Farm Records, 1961-1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Inventory Pine Ridge, Sunny Slope, Blosser, Ralston, and Glendale farms for 1964, Sheep records from 1965.
  - Cattle Records, 1949-1960 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Beef Cattle Record of Performance for 1953, Miscellaneous Animal Husbandry Record Sheet, Summary of Va. BCIA Performance Testing Program for 1955, Virginia State Department of Agriculture- Division of Markets.
  - Cattle Records, 1961-1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Virginia BCIA Calf Data Sheet.
  - Bull and Cow Records with Weight and Measures, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Contract Reports, 1937-1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Agreement with Garber Church of the Brethren, Deed of Trust, Oil and Gas Lease.
  - Certificate and Registration Records, 1942-1965 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Certificate of War Necessity, Official Health Certificate from the Division of Livestock Industry, Turkey Breeding Flock Certificate, American Beef Cattle Performance Registry Association Membership Certificate, Certificate of Record of Official Calfhood Vaccination, American Angus Association- Classification Certificate, Certificate of Entry for Performance Registry International.
  - General Records, 1942-1962 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Miscellaneous Animal Husbandry Record Sheet, Daily Record Form for the Division of Motor Transport, Report of PPLO Tube Agglutination Test.
  - Government Reports and Testing, 1950-1959 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Flock Inspection and Check-Testing Report-United States Department of Agriculture, Report of Official Vaccination for Brucellosis- Virginia Department of Agriculture, Laboratory Report of Agglutination Blood Test for Brucellosis- Virginia Department of Agriculture, Flock Selection and Pullorum Testing Report- Virginia Department of Agriculture.
  - Government Reports and Testing, 1960-1965 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Laboratory Report-Department of Agriculture and Immigration, Flock Selection and Pullorum Testing Report- Virginia Department of Agriculture, Brucellosis Calfhood Vaccination Record, Tuberculosis Test Record.
  - Insurance Records, 1950-1959 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Virginia Farm Bureau Mutual Insurance Company, Nationwide Life Insurance Company-Statement of Claim.
  - Insurance Records, 1960-1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    A Plan for Low Cost Life Insurance for Officers and Employees of Wampler Feed & Seed Company, Nationwide Life Insurance Company- Statement of Claim.
- Series 2: Correspondence, 1918-1971
  Series 2: Correspondence, 1918-1971, consists of letters ranging in date from 1918 to 1972. Early correspondence to and from Charles Wampler Sr. in regard to his turkey business and his position as county farm agent may be found here. Through the 1940s, the letters concern both agricultural and World War II topics as the Wampler businesses supported the American war effort through food production. Intermixed throughout this range are letters regarding both the financial and agricultural support Charles Wampler Jr. provided to colleges and universities through his service on their Boards of Visitors. Letters written during his terms as a state representative can be found in the 1950s and 1960s with some addressed to Virginia governors and politician Harry F. Byrd. Wampler's letters to congressmen and state representatives regarding local and national issues document his own political persuasions on sundry topics including gambling, the United Nations, and presidential candidates. The Wamplers' philanthropic pursuits and financial donations to various non-profits (Virginia League for Planned Parenthood, Virginia Council on Health and Medical Care, etc.) are also documented.
  - Correspondence, March 1918-November 1919 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, December 1919 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, January 1920 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, February 1920 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Commonwealth of Virginia- Dairy and Food Division.
  - Correspondence, March 1920 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, April 1920 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, May 1920 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, June 1920 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, July-November 1920 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Commonwealth of Virginia- Department of Agriculture and Immigration.
  - Correspondence, 1921-1927 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, January 1928 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, February 1928 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, March 1928 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, April 1928 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, July 1928 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, October 1928 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, November 1928 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Norfolk and Western Railway Co.
  - Correspondence, December 1928 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, January 1929 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, March 1929 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, April 1929 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, May 1929 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, August 1929 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, September 1929 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, October 1929 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, November 1929 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, December 1929 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, January 1930 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, February 1930 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, March 1930 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, July 1930 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, September 1930 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, December 1930 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, January 1931 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, February 1931 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, March 1931 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, May 1931 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, June 1931 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, July 1931 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, January 1932-February 1938 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    Walter S. Newman- Supervisor of Agricultural Education for the Commonwealth of Virginia.
  - Correspondence, July 1939 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, May-September 1940 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, February-December 1941 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    Poultry and Egg National Board.
  - Correspondence, January-February 1942 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Senator Aubrey Weaver, L.M. Walker Jr. - Commissioner of Agriculture Richmond, Virginia, War Department- Highway Traffic Advisory Committee, Truck and Bus Inventory for National Defense.
  - Correspondence, March-April 1942 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    War Department- Highway Traffic Advisory Committee, National Poultry Defense Committee, Senator Harry F. Byrd, Congressman A. Willis Robertson.
  - Correspondence, May-June 1942 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Congressman A. Willis Robertson, Governor Colgate Darden Jr., Selective Service Board, Thomas P. Thompson- State Chairman of the Defense Savings Staff for the Treasury Department, John L. Stewart- Acting Chief of the Division of Foreign Agricultural Research for the United States Department of Agriculture, B.C. Moomaw Jr.- Deputy Administrator of the Defense Savings Staff for the Treasury Staff.
  - Correspondence, July-August 1942 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    R.F. Nelson- Administrator of the Defense Savings Staff, Congressman A. Willis Robertson, Clarence Cannon- House of Representatives, Senator Harry F. Byrd, G.B.L. Arner- Chief of the Foreign Agricultural Research Division for the U.S. Department of Agriculture.
  - Correspondence, September-October 1942 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    United States Department of Agriculture Agricultural Marketing Administration, A.M. Alexander- Deputy Administrator of the War Savings Staff for the Treasury Department, A.D. Oderkirk- Acting Head for the Poultry and Egg Section of the Food Price Division for the Office of Price Administration, Congressman John W. Flannagan Jr., Senator Harry F. Byrd.
  - Correspondence, November-December 1942 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Madison College, The Virginia School for the Deaf and Blind, Treasury Department War Savings Staff, Congress of the United States House of Representatives, United States Department of Agriculture Farm Credit Administration, United States Department of Agriculture USDA War Board, United States Senate Committee on Rules, Commonwealth of Virginia Department of Agriculture and Immigration.
  - Correspondence, January-February 1943 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    Commonwealth of Virginia Department of Agriculture and Immigration, The National Turkey Federation, National Poultry Defense Committee.
  - Correspondence, March-April 1943 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    United States Department of Agriculture Agricultural Research Administration Bureau of Animal Industry, American Red Cross, The Virginia State Poultry Federation, Harrisonburg-Rockingham War Savings Committee.
  - Correspondence, May-June 1943 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    Emergency Committee for Food Production, Office of Price Administration, Treasury Department-War Savings Staff, United States Department of Agriculture Food Distribution Administration.
  - Correspondence, July-August 1943 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    Treasury Department-Internal Revenue Service, Commonwealth of Virginia Department of Agriculture and Immigration.
  - Correspondence, September-October 1943 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Treasury Department-Defense Savings Staff.
  - Correspondence, November-December 1943 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Commonwealth of Virginia Department of Agriculture and Immigration.
  - Correspondence, January 1944 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, August-November 1944 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, December 1944 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, January 1945 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    Senator Harry F. Byrd, Congressman A. Willis Robertson, Members of the Appeal Board of Selective Service, Governor William M. Tuck.
  - Correspondence, February 1945 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Elena Becker- Consultant in Home Economics for the Department of Public Welfare of the Commonwealth of Virginia, Commonwealth of Virginia Department of Agriculture and Immigration, Governor Colgate W. Darden Jr.
  - Correspondence, March 1945 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    Frank E. Moone- United States Department of Agriculture Bureau of Animal Industry, H.L. Shrader- Senior Extension Poultry Husbandman for the United States Department of Agriculture Extension Service, Congressman A. Willis. Robertson.
  - Correspondence, April 1945 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    Commonwealth of Virginia- Department of Finance Division of Motor Vehicles, D.K. Christenberry Jr.- Assistant Director for the Department of Mental Hygiene and Hospitals of the Commonwealth of Virginia, E.J. Milligan- Selective Service System.
  - Correspondence, May 1945 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    D.K. Christenberry Jr. - Assistant Director for the Department of Mental Hygiene and Hospitals of the Commonwealth of Virginia.
  - Correspondence, June 1945 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    L.M. Walker Jr. – Commissioner of the Department of Agriculture and Immigration for the Commonwealth of Virginia, Selective Service Board, National Poultry Defense Committee.
  - Correspondence, July 1945 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Congressman A. Willis Robertson.
  - Correspondence, August 1945 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, September 1945 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, October 1945 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, November 1945 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    Governor Colgate W. Darden Jr.
  - Correspondence, December 1945 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    Senator Harry F. Byrd.
  - Correspondence, January 1946 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    City Planning Commission for the City of Harrisonburg, Congressman A. Willis Robertson, Senator J.A. Garber.
  - Correspondence, February 1946 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, March 1946 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    Hollis Shomo- Supervisor of Department of Agriculture and Immigration for the Commonwealth of Virginia.
  - Correspondence, April 1946 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, May 1946 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, June 1946 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, July 1946 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, August 1946 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    H.C. Givens- State Veterinarian of the Department of Agriculture and Immigration for the Commonwealth of Virginia.
  - Correspondence, September 1946 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    Commonwealth of Virginia Division of Motor Vehicles.
  - Correspondence, October 1946 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    Governor William M. Tuck, Major Charles S. Roller Jr., the Virginia League for Planned Parenthood, Inc.
  - Correspondence, November 1946 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, December 1946 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, January 1947 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    Senator A. Willis Robertson, T.C. Byerly- Senior Poultry Husbandman for the United States Department of Agriculture Bureau of Animal Industry, Colonel James P. Woods, Governor William M. Tuck.